Guide to the Linebarger Family Papers 1877-1945
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Linebarger Family papers
1877-1945
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 281
Linebarger Family
2.0 linear feet
This collection includes a broad range of correspondence and informal financial records for early Montana settler David H. Linebarger; correspondence and laundry account records for his wife, Dora Linebarger; minimal correspondence and a document for their son, Walter L.Linebarger; a recipe and general notebook for Della Meyers; W.P.A. documents and correspondence regarding Elmer C. Linebarger's work as a farmer, commodities clerk, and finally as an employee of the War Department; and a wide range of photographs.
Biographical Note
David H. Linebarger was born in December 1837, in Missouri. By at least 1877, he resided in Montana and was active in community and state politics as Treasurer of Jefferson County, Montana, and his later work with the Democratic Executive Committee from his home in Gilt Edge, Montana. Although listed as a day laborer in the 1900 Montana census, prior to and after that time, David H. Linebarger worked as a miner and speculated in a variety of mining operations in and around Gilt Edge, Montana.
By 1900 David H. Linebarger had been married to Dora Linebarger for some time. Dora Linebarger was born in April, 1868, in Missouri. At the time of the 1900 census, the Linebarger's had a daughter, Maud, born in August, 1891, and a son, Walter L., born in 1893. The couple had at least one more son, Elmer Clinton, who was born March 12, 1905. Dora Linebarger likely worked as a laundress to support herself and family as David A. Linebarger, thirty years her senior, grew infirm and then died. By 1920, Dora, Walter, and fourteen-year-old Elmer Linebarger all lived in Garfield County, Montana. Twenty-seven-year-old Walter Linebarger listed his occupation as farmer in the 1920 Montana census. Dora Linebarger died in the early months of 1945.
By the time of the Great Depression, Elmer C. Linebarger still lived in Garfield County and in 1935 received a federal crop loan for his mother's farm, as well as one for his own farm in 1936. In 1936 Elmer Linebarger took a job as the Commodity Clerk for the Garfield County Relief Office. He held this position at least until 1940. Elmer and his wife Pearl had a baby girl, Doloris Jean, on October 28, 1939. In late 1942 through a war service appointment, he became a Driver Firefighter in the Fort Peck District of Montana. According to family correspondence, Elmer Linebarger and his family were still in Fort Peck, Montana, in 1945.
This collection includes a broad range of correspondence and informal financial records for David H. Linebarger from 1877 through 1909; correspondence and laundry account records for Dora Linebarger from 1908 up to 1930; minimal correspondence, an autograph album and a document for Walter L. Linebarger; an autograph album belonging to Maud Linebarger; a recipe and general notebook for Della Meyers; W.P.A. documents and correspondence regarding Elmer C. Linebarger's work as a farmer, commodities clerk, and finally as an employee of the War Department with a time span from 1935 through 1945; and a wide range of photographs likely from at least 1875 through 1910, most of which are unlabeled.
The collection is divided into six series:
Series I: David H. Linebarger, 1870-1909, 0.6 linear ft.
Series II: Dora Linebarger, 1908-1930, 0.1 linear ft.
Series III: Walter L. Linebarger, 1907-1931, 3 folders
Series IV: Elmer C. Linebarger, 1936-1945, 0.2 linear ft.
Series V: Della Meyers, undated, 1 folder
Series VI: Photographs, 1875 - circa 1940, 1 linear ft.
Series VII: Maud Linebarger, 1907, 1 item
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Gift of Mrs. J.D. Heath, 1966.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Business records--Montana; Family papers--Montana--Garfield County; Family papers--Montana--Giltedge; Photographs--Montana; Recipes--Montana
Agriculture--Montana--Garfield County; Depressions--1929--Montana--Garfield County; Fire fighters--Montana--Fort Peck; Public welfare--Montana--Garfield County--Officials and employees; Sewing; Women--Employment--Montana--Garfield County; Women--Employment--Montana--Giltedge
Fort Peck (Mont.); Garfield County (Mont.)--Social conditions; Giltedge (Mont.)
United States. Work Projects Administration; United States. War Dept.
Linebarger, David H., b. 1837; Linebarger, Dora, 1868-1945; Linebarger, Elmer C. (Elmer Clinton), 1905-1967; Meyers, Della; Linebarger, Maud, b. 1891; Meyers, Della
Montana; Photographs; Agriculture; Mines and Mineral Resources; Women
- David H. Linebarger, 1870-1909; Series I; 0.6 linear ft.
  This series includes personal and business correspondence, legal documents regarding mining claims and water rights, ephemera, and a quantity of pocket-sized notebooks used primarily as relatively informal records of income and expenses for various mining ventures. The correspondence and legal documents have been arranged chronologically as a group after which the pocket-sized notebooks are similarly ordered.
  - Letter from Isaac Butts discussing, among other topics, Butts' courtship of a Dora Graham, 1890 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from Clark & Co., 1893 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from W.W. Woods, 1893 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from J.H. Foss, 1893 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter to J.H. Foss, 1893 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from E.I. Stagner, 1894 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from J.P. Hanck, 1895 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Telegram from Conway, birth announcement, 1889 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from National Association Of Democratic Clubs, 1900 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Bill for Democratic State Central Committee, 1900 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter from Democratic Central Committee, 1900 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Letter From Democratic Executive Committee, 1900 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Note of expenses, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Two social invitations, 1903 and undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Report of Treasurer (D.A. Linebarger) of Jefferson County, Montana, 1877 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Misc. financial records, bills and receipts, 1888-1905 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Legal documents relating to mining claims, 1884-1889 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Legal documents pertaining to irrigation and water rights, 1891 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Mining claim assignment, 1891 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Loan collection records, 1892 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Clipping, legal notice regarding mine improvements, 1885 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Misc. lists of names & grocery lists, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Ephemera including social invitations, dance cards, Western Federation Miner's membership card, a wedding announcement, and a Utah tourist pamphlet, ca. 1903-1906 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Pocket-size (1 1/2"X 4") notebook from IXL Bazaar (store) used for names, addresses, expenses, and probable investment figures, 1884-1890 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Notebook, 3"X 6" with grocery or grubstake lists, mining notes, and smaller notebook in back compartment, 1886 and undated (Box-folder 1/9)
  - First National Bank, Helena, Montana bankbook, 1889 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Pocket notebook listing expenses particularly grubstake costs, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Time Book, mostly notes, 1870-1886 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Bank of Fergus County, Lewistown, Montana checkbook, 1891 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Pocket-size (1 1/2" X 4") calendar daybook from Fergus County Bank, 1904 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Kidder County State Bank, Steele, ND checkbook, 1905 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Notebook, 3" X 6", with grocery grubstake lists; records quantity of zinc mined; scribbled figuring on letter to D.A. Linebarger and family from N.E. Butts slipped into later pages of notebook, 1897-1900 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Notebook, 3" X 6", with miscellaneous expenses, 1897 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Notebook, 3" X 6", milk and other food expenses, 1897 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Notebook, 3" X 6", clothing and other expenses, 1896 and 1897 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Notebook, 3" X 5", boarding and food accounts, 1897 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Notebook, grubstake expenses and zinc mining record, 1897 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Notebook, boarding income, 1897 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Notebook, income and expense, 1897 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Notebook, grubstake expense, undated (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Notebook, grubstake expenses and zinc mining record, 1901 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Notebook, grubstake expenses, undated (Box-folder 1/26)
  - B.F. Avery & Sons Notebook, few notations, 1888-1889 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Pierce's Memorandum Account Book, 1901 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Notebook, miscellaneous financial notes, 1903 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Notebook, miscellaneous financial notes, 1905 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Notebook, miscellaneous egg & dairy income, 1903-1907 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Farmer's Rapid Calculator Notebook, undated (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Springfield Fire & Insurance Co. Calendar Notebook, 1909 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Dora Linebarger, 1908-1930; Series II; 0.1 linear ft.
  This series includes personal correspondence from a doctor and from Dora Linebarger's son and husband, a homestead patent from 1923, and sewing account books from 1908 through 1923. The group is arranged in chronological order.
  - Letter from Dr. J.J. Carroll, undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Letter from son Walter, 1930 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Letter from D.H. Linebarger, 1910 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Homestead patent to Dora Linebarger, 1923 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Laundry Account Book, 1908-1910 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Laundry Account Book and other notes, 1910-1923 (Box-folder 2/11)
- Walter L. Linebarger, 1907-1931; Series III; 3 folders
  This series includes one letter from 1926, one auto repair receipt from 1929, and one land sale contract from 1931 arranged in chronological order.
  - Letter written to E.C. Linebarger, 1926 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Auto repair receipt, 1929 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Land sale contract, 1931 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Autograph album, 1907 (Box-folder 2/14)
- Elmer C. Linebarger, 1936-1945; Series IV; 0.2 linear ft.
  This series includes farm relief correspondence from 1935 and 1936, extensive correspondence and directives from the WPA of Montana, the Montana Relief Commission, and other organizations involved in distribution of goods to needy families during the Great Depression, Linebarger's appointment as a Department of Defense civilian employee in 1942, and a small amount of miscellaneous materials such as a family letter, birth information, and news clippings.
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Farm Relief Correspondence, 1936 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - WPA Commodity Distribution Relief Correspondence to Elmer C. Linebarger, Commodity Clerk, Jordan, Montana, 1936 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Correspondence received from WPA of Montana, Montana Relief Commission and other organizations regarding relief commodities, 1937 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Correspondence received from WPA of Montana, Montana Relief Commission and other organizations regarding relief commodities, 1938 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Commodity container sale receipt, 1939 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - I.D. Card for Surplus Commodities, WPA Employee Identification Card, one bid for commodity container, 1940 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Commodity distribution correspondence, undated (Box-folder 2/21)
  - USDA Crop Allotment, 1941 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - War Department Report of Field Personnel Action, 1942 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - War Department Household Goods Receipt, Garfield County Property Tax Receipt and Garfield County Tax Receipt, 1942 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Letter to "Elmer and all" from a cousin Dona, 1945 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - News clippings, articles, and a "Care of Baby" pamphlet with announcement of birth of daughter to Elmer Clinton and Pearl Eileen Linebarger, October 28, 1939 (Box-folder 2/26)
- Della Meyers, undated; Series V; 1 folder
  This series includes a single notebook with recipes and miscellaneous notes.
  - Notebook, undated (Box-folder 2/27)
- Maud Linebarger, 1907; Series VII; 1 folder
  - Autograph album, 1907 (Box-folder 2/28)
- Photographs, 1875-circa 1940; Series VI; 1 linear ft.
  This series includes family photographs as well as individual portrait photos covering a span of time from approximately 1875 to as late as the 1940s. Most photos are not labeled with the names of the subjects, and only one is dated.
  - [Unidentified infant in christening gown], [undated]; 281(VI):1 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - [Father, mother, child], [undated]; 281(VI):2 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):3 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - [Unidentified woman, photo mount from Plank, Canastota, New York], [undated]; 281(VI):4 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - [Unidentified woman, photo mount from G.W. Fox, Sioux Falls, South Dakota], [undated]; 281(VI):5 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - [Two boys, unidentified, photograph mount from W.H. Culver, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):6 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - [Unidentified man, photo mount from W. H. Culver, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):7 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - [Unidentified man & woman, circa late 1800s], [undated]; 281(VI):8 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - [Unidentified woman, photo mount from W.H. Culver, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):9 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):10 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - [Unidentified man & woman, wedding portrait, photograph mount from Raitt, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):11 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Full length photo, Miss Florence Hovis, undated; 281(VI):12 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - [Unidentified woman, likely wearing a candy striper or nurse trainee uniform], [undated]; 281(VI):13 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - [Unidentified older man, blurred focus], [undated]; 281(VI):14 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - [Unidentified husband and wife, formal photo], [undated]; 281(VI):15 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - [Unidentified infant in pram], [undated]; 281(VI):16 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - [Same unidentified infant in pram with young girl alongside], [undated]; 281(VI):17 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - [Unidentified boys, probably brothers], [undated]; 281(VI):18 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - [Unidentified adults, one man, three women, formal photo], [undated]; 281(VI):19 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - [Unidentified infant in christening gown], [undated]; 281(VI):20 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - [Presumed but unidentified parents, son, and 3 daughters posed outdoors in front of house], [undated]; 281(VI):21 (Box-folder 3/21)
  - [Unidentified man (possibly Julian from inscription), photograph mount from Manhattan photograph Co., New York City], [undated]; 281(VI):22 (Box-folder 3/22)
  - [Unidentified woman, head shot in profile], [undated]; 281(VI):23 (Box-folder 3/23)
  - [Young girl, named Filarene Havis, per note on back], [undated]; 281(VI):24 (Box-folder 3/24)
  - [Young man in military uniform, named Bob per inscription], [undated]; 281(VI):25 (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Unidentified woman with infant and two young girls in front of house/cabin in forest], [undated]; 281(VI):26 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - [Unidentified man and woman, head shots, formal photograph], [undated]; 281(VI):27 (Box-folder 3/27)
  - [Unidentified older man, formal photograph], [undated]; 281(VI):28 (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Scenic photographof old bridge, labeled Indian Creek, Montana, undated; 281(VI):29 (Box-folder 3/29)
  - [Unidentified man and woman, formal photograph, photograph mount from Tippett, Billings, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):30 (Box-folder 3/30)
  - [Two unidentified men and two women, formal posed photograph with studio backdrop, women wearing long dresses], [undated]; 281(VI):31 (Box-folder 3/31)
  - [Unidentified man and woman, formal photograph, photograph mount from Coulter, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):32 (Box-folder 3/32)
  - [Unidentified man in front of rustic cabin/house, photograph overexposed], [undated]; 281(VI):33 (Box-folder 3/33)
  - [Two unidentified men and two woman, formal posed photograph, women wearing long skirts, photograph mount from Coulter Studio, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):34 (Box-folder 3/34)
  - [Glass-mounted photograph of unidentified girl and boy], [undated]; 281(VI):35 (Box-folder 3/35)
  - [Unidentified man, three women, girl, and boy posed in various spots in front of two-story frame house], [undated]; 281(VI):36 (Box-folder 3/36)
  - [Family photo, 4 unidentified men, 4 women, 2 boys, and 1 African American woman], [undated]; 281(VI):37 (Box-folder 3/37)
  - [Family photo, unidentified man, woman, young woman, female toddler, and 2 boys], [undated]; 281(VI):38 (Box-folder 3/38)
  - [Negative, unidentified man standing in front of rough wood door], [undated]; 281(VI):39 (Box-folder 3/39)
  - Martha Johnson, undated; 281(VI):40 (Box-folder 3/40)
  - [Unidentified baby in christening gown], [undated]; 281(VI):41 (Box-folder 3/41)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):42 (Box-folder 3/42)
  - [Unidentified man and woman, photograph marked from O.C. Bundy Studio], [undated]; 281(VI):43 (Box-folder 3/43)
  - [Unidentified young woman], [undated]; 281(VI):44 (Box-folder 3/44)
  - [Three unidentified men], [undated]; 281(VI):45 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - [Partial photo/postcard of woman in fancy hat], [undated]; 281(VI):46 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Hazel Belle Sullivan, undated; 281(VI):47 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - [Unidentified woman, small formal photograph in frame], [undated]; 281(VI):48 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - [Unidentified man, small formal photograph in frame], [undated]; 281(VI):49 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - [Unidentified boy, small formal photograph in frame], [undated]; 281(VI):50 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Matty Whitner, toddler, undated; 281(VI):51 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Maggie Whitner, baby, undated; 281(VI):52 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - [Unidentified but notably well-dressed older man], [undated]; 281(VI):53 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - [Unidentified baby], [undated]; 281(VI):54 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):55 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - [Grandmother Linebarger and unidentified baby], [undated]; 281(VI):56 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):57 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):58 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - [Postcard/photograph of unidentified man and two unidentified women in car, (addressed to Dora Linebarger)], [undated]; 281(VI):59 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - [Unidentified young woman], [undated]; 281(VI):60 (Box-folder 4/16)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):61 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - [Family photograph #1, unidentified man (father?)], [undated]; 281(VI):62 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - [Family photograph #2, unidentified woman (mother?)], [undated]; 281(VI):63 (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Family photograph #3, Martha Johnson, girl, undated; 281(VI):64 (Box-folder 4/20)
  - [Family photograph #4, Jacob, boy], [undated]; 281(VI):65 (Box-folder 4/21)
  - [Family photograph #5, unidentified girl], [undated]; 281(VI):66 (Box-folder 4/22)
  - [Family photograph #6, Mary Jane, girl], [undated]; 281(VI):67 (Box-folder 4/23)
  - [Family photograph #7, Cora Graham, girl], [undated]; 281(VI):68 (Box-folder 4/24)
  - [Family photograph #8, Charly Graham, boy], [undated]; 281(VI):69 (Box-folder 4/25)
  - [Family photograph #9, woman], [undated]; 281(VI):70 (Box-folder 4/26)
  - [Family photograph #10, small boy], [undated]; 281(VI):71 (Box-folder 4/27)
  - [Family photograph #11, Jebbie Johnson, small boy], [undated]; 281(VI):72 (Box-folder 4/28)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):73 (Box-folder 4/29)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):74 (Box-folder 4/30)
  - [Unidentified woman, full-length photo, long dress, W H. Culver Studio, Lewistown, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):75 (Box-folder 4/31)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):76 (Box-folder 4/32)
  - Mary Linebarger, undated; 281(VI):77 (Box-folder 4/33)
  - [Unidentified man], [Sept. 8, 1875]; 281(VI):78 (Box-folder 4/34)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):79 (Box-folder 4/35)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):80 (Box-folder 4/36)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):81 (Box-folder 4/37)
  - [Unidentified man], [undated]; 281(VI):82 (Box-folder 4/38)
  - Rosey Linebarger with baby, undated; 281(VI):83 (Box-folder 4/39)
  - Sarah A. Graham, undated; 281(VI):84 (Box-folder 4/40)
  - [Two unidentified woman wearing long dresses, outdoors by tree], [undated]; 281(VI):85 (Box-folder 4/41)
  - [Unidentified young man], [undated]; 281(VI):86 (Box-folder 4/42)
  - [Unidentified girl, photo from M.A. Eckert, Artist, Helena, Montana], [undated]; 281(VI):87 (Box-folder 4/43)
  - [Unidentified woman], [undated]; 281(VI):88 (Box-folder 4/44)